The third subtype of anemia is normocytic anemia.
And recall, based on the paradigm that we've established
when we discussed both microcytic and macrocytic anemias,
that a normocytic anemia will be defined by the fact
that there is an anemia, i.e. a decrease in red blood cell mass.
However, the red blood cells are normal-sized.
And again, the key measure of size that we've been using
is the MCV, or the mean corpuscular volume.
And in a normocytic anemia, the MCV will be normal,
which is between 80 and 100.
Now, in normocytic anemias, the key differential diagnosis
is, is the anemia due to peripheral destruction,
i.e., are the red blood cells being destroyed
outside of the bone marrow,
or is the anemia due to underproduction,
i.e., is the bone marrow not making red blood cells?
And the way we can distinguish between these two etiologies
is to look at the reticulocyte count.
Reticulocytes are young red blood cells
that are obviously released from the bone marrow.
You can think of them as baby red blood cells.
On a blood smear, they're identified as cells
that are slightly larger than normal,
just a tad bit larger, with bluish cytoplasm.
And the bluish cytoplasm is due to residual RNA
within the cell.
Basically, when the young red blood cell is born,
it's born with no nucleus,
and it has most of its hemoglobin.
However, there is some residual processing of RNA
and protein synthesis that continues to occur
in the first day or so after birth.
Reticulocytes look like this.
Here's a red blood cell smear,
and you can see that there is this one cell
that's just a tad larger than the others
and that has this bluish hue to its cytoplasm.
And again, the bluish hue is due to the presence of RNA
within the cytoplasm.
It's important to know why the reticulocyte looks blue.
Now, normally, the reticulocyte count
in the peripheral blood smear is about 1 to 2%.
Each day, about 1 to 2% of cells
are removed from the circulation
and replaced by reticulocytes.
In a properly functioning bone marrow,
the reticulocyte count, if there was an anemia,
should pump up to greater than 3%.
What I mean by this is that when there is an anemia,
the bone marrow should respond
by making more reticulocytes
in order to try to make up for the loss of red blood cells.
And the bone marrow does have the ability
to pump up the reticulocyte production
so that the reticulocyte count
in the peripheral blood smear would be greater than 3%.
However, we also need to keep in mind
that with an anemia,
the reticulocyte count will be falsely elevated.
And that's because the reticulocytes
are measured as a percentage
of the total red blood cells.
Let's assume that a patient has 98 red blood cells
and two of those red blood cells are reticulocytes.
So then this would mean that the reticulocyte count
in a normal patient is 2 out of 100.
98 plus 2 is 100, so 2 out of 100.
And therefore, the reticulocyte count is 2%.
Now, let's imagine that the patient gets an anemia.
If the patient gets an anemia,
if we assume that 50 of these 98 red blood cells
get destroyed or about half of the cells get destroyed,
then the patient would have 48 red blood cells.
And because the vast majority of what gets destroyed
are going to be the normal red blood cells,
the patient would have two reticulocytes.
And so now the patient has two out of 50.
48 plus 2 is 50, 2 over 50, which is really 4 over 100,
or 4%.
Now, you see that the reticulocyte count went up to 4%.
However, has the bone marrow made any extra red blood cells
in this circumstance?
The answer is no.
It's still making those same two reticulocytes.
And so you can see that in a patient with anemia,
the reticulocyte count is falsely elevated.
And that's what I was trying to say here in your text,
that a decrease in total red blood cells falsely elevates
the percentage of reticulocytes.
Therefore, in order to adjust for the anemia,
we need to correct the reticulocyte count.
And how do we correct the reticulocyte count?
By multiplying it by the hematocrit divided by 45.
That then would correct the reticulocyte count.
So let's go back to the whiteboard.
Remember in our example, the patient normally had 98 cells
and two reticulocytes giving a percentage of 2%.
And then the patient got an anemia so that half of their red blood cells were destroyed.
So roughly 48 red blood cells are present.
And then the reticulocyte count remained 2.
And we said that that reticulocyte count now becomes 4%, 2 over 50.
Well, in essence, this anemia represents a destruction of about half of the red blood cells.
And so the way we would correct this 4% is to take the 4% and multiply it by the patient's hematocrit
over the normal hematocrit, which is about 45.
So let's say that the patient has lost half of their red blood cells.
Their hematocrit would be half of normal, about 23.
So 23 over 45 would be approximately 1 half, just roughly.
Obviously, 23 over 46 is 1 half.
But this would be 1 half times 4%, which would then bring our reticulocyte count,
our corrected reticulocyte count, down to 2%.
And so by looking at the corrected reticulocyte count,
we realize that the bone marrow really is not responding well, in this particular example,
to the stress of the anemia.
And therefore, we would say that there is a problem with bone marrow function.
Now, again, this is a very important discussion
because when we have a normal cytokinemia, we have to start by asking ourselves a very simple question.
Are the cells being destroyed outside of the bone marrow,
or are the cells not being produced by the bone marrow?
And if the corrected reticulocyte count is greater than 3%,
we know that the bone marrow is producing red blood cells, fine.
But if the corrected reticulocyte count is less than 3%,
then we know that there could be a problem with the bone marrow.
So correcting the reticulocyte count is a relatively high-yield concept.
When we think about destruction of red blood cells in the periphery,
i.e. the bone marrow is making red blood cells fine,
but the cells are being destroyed in the periphery, that's called hemolysis.
And hemolysis can be divided into extravascular and intravascular hemolysis.
In extravascular hemolysis, the red blood cells are destroyed by the reticuloendothelial system,
the macrophages of the spleen, the liver, and the lymph nodes,
and this occurs outside of the blood vessel.
In intravascular hemolysis, the red blood cells are destroyed within the blood vessel.
Now in both cases, we're going to get an anemia because we're destroying red blood cells,
but there will be a good bone marrow response.
That is, the bone marrow will be producing greater than 3% reticulocytes
if we look at the corrected reticulocyte count.
It's important to be aware of the basic principles that underlie each of the types of hemolysis
so that we can understand the clinical findings that will be seen
if there is extravascular or intravascular hemolysis.
So let's start with extravascular hemolysis.
Recall that I said that in extravascular hemolysis,
the red blood cells are destroyed by the reticuloendothelial system.
The reticuloendothelial system is made up of the macrophages of the spleen, liver, and the lymph nodes,
and the macrophages, they consume red blood cells and then break down the hemoglobin.
When they eat the red blood cells, they break down the hemoglobin,
and it's broken down as follows.
The globin, which is made up of amino acids, it's a simple protein,
is broken down into amino acids.
The heme, which is composed of iron and protoporphyrin, is broken down into iron and protoporphyrin.
The iron is recycled by the body,
and the protoporphyrin is subsequently broken down into unconjugated bilirubin.
Now, of course, the unconjugated bilirubin will then be bound to the serum albumin
and delivered to the liver for conjugation and excretion into the bile.
So the unconjugated bilirubin goes into the serum.
It is not water-soluble.
It is fat-soluble.
It will remain within the serum until the liver can take it and conjugate it,
and then the liver, once it's conjugated, will put it into the bile.
So patients who have extravascular hemolysis will have clinical findings that are based on this paradigm.
Of course, they will have anemia because they are destroying red blood cells.
They will have splenomegaly because the spleen is consuming those red blood cells,
and this is an example of hypertrophy.
In addition, the patients will have jaundice.
Why do they have jaundice?
Well, let's explain that.
If the patient is producing from the spleen unconjugated bilirubin,
that unconjugated bilirubin will go to the liver,
and it's in the liver, this being the liver, where it becomes conjugated bilirubin,
and the conjugated bilirubin will eventually be dumped into the gallbladder.
So that's the paradigm.
Now let's pretend that the liver normally has the ability to conjugate about 10 molecules every second.
It has the ability to conjugate 10 molecules of unconjugated bilirubin every second.
Now let's say that normally, just by the turnover of red blood cells,
remember that the spleen is where the destruction of red blood cells occurs,
even when blood cells are turning over every 120 days.
So let's say that the spleen spits out five molecules of unconjugated bilirubin.
That's the normal, and we wouldn't have any problem with jaundice.
In the case of extravascular hemolysis, the patient is destroying red blood cells at a much higher rate.
And so instead of five molecules of unconjugated bilirubin every second,
this may go up to 20 molecules of unconjugated bilirubin every second.
Now these 20 molecules are going to override the conjugating ability of the liver,
and so therefore what's going to happen is that there's going to be an excess of bilirubin floating around in the blood,
unconjugated bilirubin, that is, floating around in the blood.
And because there is an excess of unconjugated bilirubin floating around in the blood,
the patients will look yellow and develop jaundice.
Again, I've explained that's due to unconjugated bilirubin.
At the same time, eventually the liver will conjugate that bilirubin,
and when it conjugates that bilirubin, it'll throw it into the bile,
and so we're going to get a supersaturation of bilirubin in the bile.
And that supersaturation of bilirubin in the bile is going to increase the risk that the bilirubin would precipitate
and form bilirubin gallstones.
And we'll talk about gallstones in much more detail when we do your liver lectures.
Finally, the patients are going to have marrow hyperplasia.
Why would they get marrow hyperplasia?
Because the bone marrow is fine, there's no problem in the bone marrow,
and so there will be hyperplasia of the cells of the bone marrow,
and the reticulocyte count will increase because the bone marrow will begin to pump out as many baby cells as possible.
And so we'll have a corrected reticulocyte count of greater than 3%.
In the case of intravascular hemolysis, the red blood cells are being destroyed within the blood vessels.
Now, destruction of the red blood cell within the blood vessel would result in the hemoglobin,
which is present within the red cell, to actually be passed directly into the blood.
And when hemoglobin gets passed into the blood, the very first response of the body
is to bind it with a scavenger molecule called haptoglobin.
Haptoglobin binds hemoglobin and takes it to the spleen to be reprocessed.
So that's one way by which the human body can save hemoglobin that might leak out of the red blood cell.
And again, why would the human body want to save hemoglobin?
Because hemoglobin has iron, and iron is classically very difficult to get a hold of.
And so the body tries to save every bit of iron that it can.
So the initial stage of loss of hemoglobin in the serum is formation of a hemoglobin-haptoglobin complex,
and therefore the patient's haptoglobin levels, the free haptoglobin levels, will actually decrease.
So that's one very early change.
Now the haptoglobin is minimal within the serum, and it really doesn't do much to save hemoglobin,
except in very small amounts.
Eventually, the next step will be that hemoglobin will build up in the blood, creating a hemoglobinemia,
and that hemoglobin will leak out into the urine because it's water-soluble, creating a hemoglobinuria.
And that allows us to understand the clinical and laboratory findings.
So these patients will have hemoglobinemia because hemoglobin will leak out into the blood.
They'll have hemoglobinuria because hemoglobin from the blood will leak out into the urine,
and they'll get hemocidinuria.
What's hemocidinuria?
Well, as the hemoglobin is going through the tubules, let's draw a tubule here.
This is the epithelial cell of the tubule.
So as, this would be the basement membrane, and this would be the lumen.
As hemoglobin is going through this tubule, some of the hemoglobin will be taken up by the renal tubular cells.
And as the hemoglobin is taken up by the renal tubular cells, it'll be destroyed, and the iron will be bound,
and it'll pile up and bind as hemocidarin.
Now as it piles up and binds as hemocidarin, it'll be in the cell,
but eventually these cells, because they're turning over, will actually slough off days after the hemolysis.
And so days later, within the urine, patients may have hemocidinuria, and that's actually a high-yield principle.
So initially, during the period of hemolysis, they get hemoglobinemia and hemoglobinuria.
And then it may be that several days later, the patient will actually have hemocidinuria as these tubular cells are being turned over,
and they fall off and then go into the urine and are loaded with the iron from the fact that they consumed hemoglobin.
Finally, there will be a decreased serum heptoglobin, and that was the very initial change that occurred with intravascular hemolysis.
Again, haptoglobin doesn't really save much of the hemoglobin, but it is an important measure
because it tells us that there is some degree of intravascular hemolysis going on.
We need to have an understanding of the reticulocyc count, intravascular hemolysis, and extravascular hemolysis
in order to then subsequently understand the anemias that we want to discuss in the subsequent sections.
So we'll stop here and then continue with discussions of extravascular, intravascular hemolysis,
and underproduction anemias in subsequent sections.